<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Core redivivus in a sermon preached at Christ-Church Tabernacle in London upon Sunday, September 9, 1683, being a day of publick thanksgiving for the deliverance of His Sacred Majesties person and government from the late treasonable rebellion and fanatick conspiracy / by William Bolton ...</title>
            <author>Bolton, William, 1650 or 51-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23230</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12494394</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12494394</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62462</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62462)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 307:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Core redivivus in a sermon preached at Christ-Church Tabernacle in London upon Sunday, September 9, 1683, being a day of publick thanksgiving for the deliverance of His Sacred Majesties person and government from the late treasonable rebellion and fanatick conspiracy / by William Bolton ...</title>
                  <author>Bolton, William, 1650 or 51-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Norris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62462:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Core Redivivus. IN A SERMON PREACHED At <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Tabernacle in <hi>London,</hi> upon Sunday, <hi>September</hi> 9. 1683.</p>
            <p>BEING A Day of Publick <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> for the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of His <hi>Sacred Majeſties Perſon</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> from the late <hi>Treaſonable Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Conſpiracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM BOLTON,</hi> one of the School-Maſters of the <hi>Charter-Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Norris,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> M.DC.LXXXIV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:62462:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62462:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Core Redivivus: A Thankſgiving SERMON, For a Deliverance from a <hi>Fanatick</hi> Conſpiracy.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>NUMB. 16. ver. 26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And he ſpake unto the Congregation, ſaying, Depart I pray you from the Tents of theſe wicked Men, and touch nothing of theirs, lest ye be conſumed in all their Sins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Context runs thus, And the Lord ſpake unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying, Speak unto the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, ſaying, Get ye up from the Tabernacle of <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> followed him: and he ſpake unto the Congregation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62462:3"/>
            <p>The Words are an Exhortation of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Supream Magiſtrate of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subjects, That they ſhould depart from the Ten's of thoſe wicked Conſpirators, <hi>Korah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> with their Aſſociates, leſt they ſhould be conſumed in their Sins.</p>
            <p>What I have to ſay upon the Words ſhall be laid out in this following method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall give you an Hiſtorical Narration of this Conſpiracy, as the Scripture doth afford Light thereto; with the Puniſhment of thoſe wicked Men, as the Holy Ghoſt calls them in my Text: which Particular being ſpoken to, I ſhall for my ſecond Part,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Draw this natural Propoſition, That all Rebellion, of what kind ſoever, is not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, but deſtructive likewiſe to Traytors, and that both in this Life and that which is to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall reflect upon the ſiniſter Practices and Opinions of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> relating to the Matter in hand; I name the latter, becauſe of their ſo known Oppoſition to Prelacy, that they ſeem to draw their Extraction from this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Triumvirate, <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>My laſt part ſhall be by way of Application.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>Firſt then, that you may the better underſtand the Hiſtory of this Chapter, be pleaſed to go
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62462:3"/>back two or three Years, and you will find theſe rebellious Perſons, with all the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> groaning under the heavy Oppreſſion of the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi> In this their miſery they cried unto the Lord, who heard their Complaints, and by a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Miracles, wrought by the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> was pleaſed to reſcue them from their cruel Task-maſters: Suppoſe them therefore on the other ſide of the <hi>Red Sea</hi> from <hi>Aegypt,</hi> free from their cruel Oppreſſors, whom they had with Joy ſeen drowned in the Sea, but yet theſe men forgat God at the Sea, even at the <hi>Red Sea.</hi> After this we find them often murmuring againſt God, and as often puniſhed, though in the midſt of Judgment God remembred Mercy; nay, they ſo provoked the Almighty at one time, that had it not been for the Prayer of this <hi>Moſes,</hi> againſt whom they conſpire in this Chapter, I ſay had not this <hi>Moſes</hi> then interceeded for them, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful as they now appear, the Lord had utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted them out from the Face of the Earth. Theſe men had often rebelled againſt the Lord, but they ſaw it was to their own Ruine; now they will try whether they may not more ſafely fly out againſt their Prince and High-Prieſt whom the Lord had ſet over them: here they think themſelves ſafe, and that God was not concerned in the Perſon of <hi>Moſes</hi> their Supream Magiſtrate.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62462:4"/>
               <p>But ſurely, my beloved, one would rather expect theſe men to have been ſtrengthning one another againſt the many Enemies, with whom they were to fight; one would have imagined to have heard theſe men offering up their Praiſes to God for the great Mercies paſt, and imploring the Continuance of his Favours upon his Servants <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> who, as they had been God's great Inſtruments in freeing this People from an horrid Slavery, ſo they might likewiſe ſettle them in the Promiſed Land; but inſtead thereof, we read in this Chapter of nothing in ſome men but Murmurings, but Repinings, but Rebellion: the chief Heads whereof are <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> who had ſupplanted from their Loyalty no leſs than two hundred and fifty Princes of the Aſſembly, men of Renown; upon whom, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the Holy Ghoſt in my Text faſtens no other Character than that of Wicked, who are here threatned to be conſumed. <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> were deſcended from the Line of <hi>Reuben,</hi> the eldeſt Son of Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> and therefore reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned themſelves more fitting to receive the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority than <hi>Moſes,</hi> who deſcended from a younger Houſe; and <hi>Korah</hi> thought himſelf as much ſlighted and contemned, in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Elizaphan</hi> the Son of <hi>Uzziel</hi> to have been made the Prince of the <hi>Kohathites</hi> (the principal Family
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62462:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of he <hi>Levites</hi> next to <hi>Gerſon</hi>) when he himſelf deſcended of the elder Brother. You may fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy them therefore in their Cabals and Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for in <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. we are told, they had no leſs than 250 Princes of the Aſſembly, and men too famous. in the Congregation, men of renown that joyned with them; I ſay, you may fancy thoſe men got together in their Tents, and <hi>Corah</hi> Addreſſing himſelf to them in this manner; I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate <hi>Korah,</hi> rather than any of the others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Conſpiracy in Scripture is called the Gain-ſaying of <hi>Korah.</hi> Suppoſe therefore <hi>Korah</hi> ſpeaking to his Aſſociates after this manner: 'Tis true indeed, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> have delivered us from the Hands of the <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> but we had better have continued there than baſely to ſubmit our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Vaſſals to our Fathers Children: We do no longer indeed make Brick of Clay, but then we were not in Subjection to our fellow-Servants: <hi>Moſes</hi> promiſed that he would bring us into a Land flowing with Milk and Honey, and behold he kills us in a Wilderneſs: If we muſt have Princes, you my Lords, <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> are more fitting to rule over us, as being of an elder Houſe than he, and if there be a Neceſſity of having one Prieſt above another in place, and power, without Oſtentation, the Mitre might ſit as well upon my head as that of <hi>Aaron:</hi> In vain,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62462:5"/>in vain we are freed from the Yoke of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> to be Slaves to thoſe, whoſe birth at the beſt is but equal to our own: As for my part I will not bear it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think ſuch generous Spirits as yours can ſubmit to ſuch a Servitude any longer. But in this Speech I would not be miſunderſtood, concerning Succeſſion; for the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Government was then perfectly Theocatical, and God himſelf was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to appoint Governours for his own People; to which <hi>Theocracy</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> the next of Kin in Blood anſwers in other Nations; I am ſure in this Kingdom; and may it always continue: After ſuch words as theſe, you may imagine the chief Conſpirators confirmed; the People now are to beſeduced, and what meaſures I beſeech you are followed? Why, They are flattered with the hopes of an Abſolute freedom, with Liberty and Property, Words, I muſt confeſs, not expreſſed, but ſufficiently implyed in this Chapter, as will appear to any who ſeriouſly read the ſame: They are made to believe that they ſhall have a Power in ſacred Matters, as ſhould both authorize and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their approaches to the Holy Altar without the intervention of Prieſt or Prelate: The People being gulled by ſuch Arts as theſe; the Leaders boldly ſhew themſelves againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and impudently tell them to their faces <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. of this Chapter, <hi>You take too much upon you ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62462:5"/>all the Congregation are Holy, even every one of them, and the Lord is among them; Wherefore then lift ye up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi> At the hearing of this, <hi>Moſes</hi> falls upon his face, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. and tells them that on the morrow, the Lord would ſhew who were his, and then gently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes theſe Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> the true Fathers of our Presbyterians; who ſcorn to acknowledge any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction above their own, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. Seemeth it but a ſmall thing to you, that the God of Iſrael hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated you from the Congregation of Iſrael to bring you near to himſelf, to do the Service of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to ſtand before the Congregation, to Miniſter unto them, and he hath brought thee near to him, and all thy Brethren, the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> and ſeek ye the Prieſt-hood al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo? for which cauſe both thou and all thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany are gathered together againſt the Lord; and what is <hi>Aaron</hi> that ye Murmur againſt him? As if he ſhould have ſaid, It is not <hi>Aaron</hi> that hath thruſt himſelf into, or invaded this Office; for he was conſecrated unto it by God himſelf. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a gentle Rebuke, he condeſcends to ſend a Meſſenger unto them, to call <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> who <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. impudently return, they will not come unto him; and not only ſo, but with moſt upbraiding terms and ſevereſt Sarcaſms, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62462:6"/>
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. endeavoured to expoſe him to the ſhame and contumely of the People. Is it a ſmall thing (ſay they) that thou haſt brought us up out of a Land that floweth with Milk and Honey, to kill us in the Wilderneſs, except thou makeſt thy ſelf altogether a Prince over us? Moreover thou haſt not brought us up into a Land that floweth with Milk and Honey, or given us Inheritance of Fields and Vineyards; wilt thou put out the Eyes of theſe Men, we will not come up? <hi>Moſes,</hi> though the meekeſt of men, yet as the following Verſe tells us, was wroth, and appeals unto the Lord as a Witneſs of his Integrity; hear himſelf ſpeaking, <hi>I have not taken one Aſs from them, neither have I hurt one of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, Beloved, you have an Account of their Conſpiracy; now be pleaſed to take a view of the end of theſe wicked Men, ſee whether they are not conſumed in their Sins: Their Sin was great, ſo likewiſe was their Puniſhment too; and that all men might be fright'ned and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from their levelling Principles, from oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their lawful Magiſtrate, and promoting a Party between the High-Prieſt and <hi>Levite,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Biſhop and Prieſt now, for I cannot but take the latter in the Chriſtian Church to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the former in the Jewiſh. <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. We read, That <hi>the Ground clave aſunder that was under them, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62462:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed them up, and their Houſes and all the men that appertained unto</hi> Korah, <hi>all their Goods, they, and all that appertained unto them, went down alive into the Pit, and the earth cloſed upon them, and they periſhed from among the Congregation.</hi> And ſo I come to my ſecond Propoſition; <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p n="2">2. That all Rebellion, of what kind ſoever, is not only unlawful, but deſtructive likewiſe to Traytors, and that in both Worlds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is unlawful; (but I ſhall only ſpeak two or three Words of this, as ſuppoſing it a Subject that hath been often handled, eſpecially at this time, by more learned men) I ſhall only ſay this, That to oppoſe our lawful Magiſtrates is againſt the Senſe and Practice of Chriſt's Church in all Ages, even under the ſevereſt Perſecutions, I ſay in all Ages, even under the ſevereſt Perſecutions of Heathen. Emperours, nay, under <hi>Julian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate;</hi> for never, never were the Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers brought in, and wrack'd to patroniſe Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion till theſe laſt Years, calculated without doubt for the <hi>Meridian</hi> of this Conſpiracy; though how much the Fathers were wronged, the Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what hath been alledged hath ſufficiently declared: But then,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Rebellion is not only unlawful, but deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive likewiſe to Traytors, in both Worlds.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62462:7"/>
               <p>Give me leave to dwell ſomewhat long upon this Particular; I ſay then, Treaſon is pernicious and deſtructive to Traytors.</p>
               <p>Good Chriſtians, If we ſhall reflect upon the judicial Proceedings of God Almighty in this kind, you will find him ſo jealous of his own, as not to ſuffer in his Deputy's Honour, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by a ſecret and irreſiſtible Power he hath ſtill countermanded the deepeſt projects of T raytors, he hath ſplit their Councils, and ſtruck their moſt refined Policies with Fruſtration and a Curſe. Hiſtories, both ſacred and profane, are full of Inſtances of this nature. You have heard how <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſuffered both in themſelves and Accomplices, for their Mutiny againſt <hi>Moſes.</hi> But becauſe people are more won by Examples than any other way of Diſcourſe, I ſhall mention ſeveral out of the Sacred Bible and our Engliſh Annals.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Out of the Bible. Let <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſteal the Hearts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>David,</hi> both his King and Father; let ten of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and proclaim him King in <hi>Hebron;</hi> let him be back'd with all the Policy of <hi>Achitophel;</hi> let the diſtreſſed <hi>David</hi> fly from his Royal Seat, and let his ungrateful and rebellious Son poſſeſs <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> let a Tent be ſpread upon the top of the Houſe, and <hi>Abſolom</hi> go in unto his Fathers Concubines
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62462:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the ſight of all Iſrael, ſo that all the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors may know, that he never expected to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to his Father; Let <hi>Achitopbel</hi> give <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> advice to purſue <hi>David,</hi> and his Followers, who were weary and faint, and in no likelihood of eſcaping, had not God been on his ſide when wicked men thus roſe up againſt him; A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry formidable Conſpiracy, this, you will ſay, but behold the Iſſue of it! the Council of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel</hi> is turned into folly, inſomuch that he is forced to lay violent hands upon himſelf; and though the too indulgent Father gives com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to the Army to ſpare this his unnatural Son; yet rather than <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſhall proſper in his Treaſon, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn beloved Hair ſhall ſerve for an Halter to execute him; you may read the whole Conſpiracy at your leaſure in <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. from <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. to the 19.</p>
               <p>Let <hi>Sheba</hi> the Son of <hi>Bichri</hi> make aparty in <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> let him ſecure himſelf in the ſtrong City of <hi>Abel,</hi> a Woman ſhall perſwade his own followers to cut off his Head, and preſent it unto <hi>Joab, Davids</hi> General, <hi>Chap.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>If you look into the 11 of 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> you will find the reward of <hi>Athaliahs</hi> Treaſon: She ſeizeth upon the Crown of <hi>Judah,</hi> and to ſecure herſelf in it, She, as ſhe imagined, ſlew all the Seed-Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: after ſix years injoyment of the Throne;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62462:8"/>without doubt, ſhe ſuppoſed herſelf ſafe enough, when Behol d the King's Son, hid in the Houſe of the Lord for ſix years ſpace, is brought forth by the Loyal <hi>Jehojada,</hi> the high Prieſt, and proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King, and the Traytoreſs <hi>Athaliah</hi> is juſtly ſlain, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. If from the ſacred Writings, I ſhould tell you what occurs from Heathen Authors of this Nature, time would fail me: Rather than <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſhall be poiſoned by his Phyſitian, his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Enemies the Romans ſhall detect the Treaſon: But what ſhould I ranſack Foreign Hiſtories for Examples of this kind? Our Engliſh Annals do afford us enough, ſince the Norman Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>Let <hi>John</hi> uſurp the Throne due to <hi>Arthur,</hi> his elder Brother's Son, he taught but his Subjects to Rebel againſt him; After he had numbred as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Troubles as dayes of his Reign; After he had proſtituted the Imperial Throne to the Luſt and Power of the Pope; After moſt of his Subjects had ſworn Allegiance to a Foreign Prince, he is thought to be poyſoned by a Monk.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, though otherwiſe a brave Prince, yet becauſe he diſpoſſeſſed his Father of the Crown, ſhall rue it in his Grand-ſon, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Succeſſor, whom <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, an Uſurper, bereaves firſt of his Throne, and a little after of his Life too: But Divine Vengeance meets with him likewiſe in his Poſterity, for <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62462:8"/>the Sixth, his Grand-ſon, though as innocent and harmleſs a Prince as ever before him enjoyed the Imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> hath his own Son ſtabb'd before his Face, and himſelf ſome time afterward butchered by the ſame hand. Let <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Third murder his innocent Nephews in the Tower, let him poyſon his own Wife, that ſo he might marry his Niece, the only Heireſs to the Throne: yet God blaſts his Deſigns, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this Nation both with the Tyrant's Death, and the happy Union of the <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in the Perſons of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh; which Conteſt had coſt more Blood than twice conquered <hi>France;</hi> which one would think ſhould make all true Engliſh men pray for the ſucceſſion of the Crown, in a true lineal Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: From theſe let us come ſome what nearer; and behold <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth upon his death Bed, that <hi>Edward</hi> who was made God's happy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in reſcuing us from the Superſtition and Idolatry of the Roman Church: <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a feign'd Proteſtant (for at his Execution he declared himſelf a Papiſt) works and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth upon the dying Prince to declare the Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi> his ſucceſſor: The ſecurity of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion was then, as now pretended, to which they knew <hi>Mary</hi> was averſe: The King ſeals the Grant to the Lady <hi>Gray,</hi> moſt of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62462:9"/>Council, with all the Judges are won or forced to confirm it. After the King's death (whether cauſed by poiſon from that pretended Abhorrer of Popery <hi>Northumberland,</hi> or otherwiſe, I ſhall not determine) The Lady <hi>Gray</hi> againſt her own will is proclaimed Queen in this City, and her ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Father-in-Law <hi>Northumberland</hi> thinks all ſafe, as having nothing to oppoſe him, but though a true, yet a naked and defenceleſs Title: When no ſooner <hi>Mary,</hi> tho a Papiſt, aſſerts her Right to the Crown, but her Subjects, though Proteſtants, as one man, riſe up in Armes to defend the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion: They knew how many thouſand lives the diſpute about the Crown had coſt but a little before; Neither could they find any motive then, no more than we can now in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that gave any Encouragement againſt the lawful Heir. Perſecution they might dread, but they would commit that cauſe to God, and they had rather under go the flames of Martyrdom than be ſtigmatized with the Brand of Rebellion. Upon this the Conſpirators were defeated, (and that without a Battel,) taken and executed. I might tell you of <hi>Wyat's</hi> Conſpiracy in the ſame Queen's time: and of many others in her moſt glorious Siſter's Reign: To theſe I might add the Conſpiracy of the Papiſts in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, and every where you will find God's miraculous deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62462:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Kings, and the wicked Traytors ſtill conſumed in their Sins. But further, Treaſon is dangerous to the Actors thereof in the World to come, I am ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation:</hi> A very ſmall encouragement, God knows, for Traytors and Conſpirators to riſe up againſt their lawful Governours. For though we ſhould grant, (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſeldom happens) that many Traitors might ſo far proſper here as to ſecure themſelves from the hands of Juſtice, yet there is a King of Kings from whom no power can ſhelter Conſpirators; And this Damnation in the Cloſe of all will prove a ſad prize of the moſt fortunate Treaſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>And ſo I come to my third particular, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To reflect upon the ſiniſter practices, as well as abſur'd Opinions, of the <hi>Roman,</hi> and <hi>Geneva</hi> Chair, or of the Jeſuits and Presbiterians relating to this Subject.</p>
               <p>And, good Chriſtians, I think I cannot be blamed for naming both theſe together, ſeeing that both of them were ſetled in the World in the ſame unhappy year. <hi>viz</hi> 1541. The one by <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> at <hi>Rome;</hi> The other by Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> at <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va:</hi> and all their practice ever ſince hath been, like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> ſvvorn Brethren in Iniquity, to plot and conſpire the death and ruine of Princes.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62462:10"/>The Jeſuit (ever ſince that Society plagued the World) hath out numbred its years with Plots and Conſpiracies: I might give you ſeveral Inſtances concerning their Diſobedience to Princes, from their moſt approved and ſignal Authors. I ſhall name two of them, joyning to them the Pope himſelf, with his full Conſiſtory. <hi>Mariana</hi> the Jeſuit in ſeveral Places, doth not only allovv of, but urgeth the Neceſſity of Killing and murdering Princes vvho are Enemies to the Catholick Religion, as they are pleaſed to phraſe it: <hi>Anno</hi> 1594, <hi>John Caſtel,</hi> a Scholar of the Jeſuits, vvith a knife vvound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of France, and ſtruck out one of his teeth, intending to have murdered him, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vvhich <hi>Caſtel</hi> vvas condemned to ſuffer; <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zois Verone</hi> undertakes the Vindication of the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, and is eloquent upon it, declaring that it vvas a generous, heroick and vertuous Act, and comparable to the moſt renovvned and great Deeds of the Ancients, either in ſacred or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Hiſtory; and concludes that he dyed a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr: But what ſhould I trouble you vvith ſuch mean Authors as Defenders of the Murderers of Princes? ſince Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> himſelf, in a full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory of Cardinals, ſpake a long Oration in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> third of <hi>France.</hi> And let them not cheat us vvith the idle diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Prince's being killed by a private or publick
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62462:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>hand; for the Queſtion is not, vvhether a Prince may be killed this vvay or that vvay, but vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any vvay at all? For it vvas as unlavvful to murther <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt by a pretended High Court of Juſtice, as to endeavour the Aſſaſſinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of his Son (our gracious Soveraign, vvhom God long preſerve) by a Blunderbuſs. Neither doth the Jeſuit only lye under this Cenſure of Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging diſobedience to their ſupream Governour; But likewiſe their Contemporaries the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. I ſhall eaſily grant, that Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the laſt Sect, hath in his Inſtitutes as much preſſed the Duty of Subjects tovvards their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as any Author vvhatſoever, yet in the unhappy diſtinction of a Publick or private Subject, and ſo making of Princes to be accountable to the Three Eſtates, hath been as deſtructive an opinion as could be broached; I am ſure this Nation hath had vvoful experience of it. But beloved, vvho could expect better fruit from Presbytery, which was begot by Rebellion and Treaſon; expelling from <hi>Geneva</hi> their lawful Magiſtrate? And though Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> was not then at <hi>Geneva,</hi> when the Prince was excluded by <hi>Farellus</hi> and <hi>Viretus,</hi> yet his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probavi ſuffragio meo,</hi> his approving of what was done by them, makes him too, too guilty. <hi>Beza,</hi> his Succeſſor in the ſame Chair, in his 24th Epiſtle ſays as much: And if he were the Author of the Book called <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyrannos,</hi> as many think, there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62462:11"/>hath been no Rebellion, ſays my Author, which may not fairly be ſuppoſed to receive encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from it. Conſult Mr. <hi>Knox,</hi> and he will tell you, 'tis not Birth or propinquity of Blood that makes a King Lawful: And what miſchief <hi>Buchanan</hi>'s Book <hi>De jure Regni apud Scotos,</hi> hath done, will appear, when the traiterous pretended High Court of Juſtice againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, drew moſt of their Pleas out of it. <hi>Paraeus</hi>'s Comment upon the <hi>Romans</hi> for encouraging theſe Doctrines of reſiſting the lawful Magiſtrate, in King <hi>James</hi>'s his time, was publickly and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burnt at <hi>Oxon;</hi> and I cannot but bleſs God for the ſame Univerſities Prudence at this time for condemning ſeveral Seditious and Factious Books, and prohibiting her Members the reading of ſuch Books. But the late Rebellion againſt the Father, and the now deſigned Aſſaſſination of his Sons, ſufficiently declare their Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Princes, and thoſe that are ſet in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over them. And thus, my Beloved, I have ſpoken to the particulars I promiſed to treat of; I ſhall now proceed to Application, and I have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <p>Firſt therefore, Did theſe wicked men in my Text, after a ſucceſſion of Miracles, in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> thraldom; Did they, I ſay, conſpire againſt their lawful Magiſtrate,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62462:11"/>and that Magiſtrate too, who had been God's great Inſtrument in reſcuing them from the hands of their cruel Task-maſters? Oh! how may we condole and lament, that the greateſt Favours and Indulgence of the meekeſt Princes, cannot oblige ſome ungrateful Subjects! Our Iſrael too is a ſufficient Evidence; for we likewiſe groaned under a moſt ſevere ſlavery: our King's Father, the anointed of the Lord, the Breath of our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, vvas taken in the nets of wicked Men, and barbarouſly murdered at his own Palace; our Loyal Nobles were either put to death or baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the beſt reformed Religion in the World diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced, and cryed down, vvhilſt the Calves of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> were erected in the Room: Our Liberty, the Glory of our Engliſh Nation, was fettered and ſhackled, and inſtead of one good King we vvere forced to ſubmit to more than 500 Tyrants: The Son of this Royal Martyr, our novv gracious Soveraign, after a miraculous eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape from <hi>Worcester</hi> vvas forced to ſhelter himſelf amongſt foreign Princes. This, and more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable than this, vvas the Condition of our <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> vvhen God, pitying our Calamities, reſtored our <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in him our Religion, and our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; and there was this difference between theirs and our <hi>Moſes;</hi> that ours did not paſs through a Sea of blood to his Kingdoms, but came to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62462:12"/>Harbour of reſt by peaceable Meaſures. His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration was as miraculous as his former Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and he that was forced from his home by a whirlwind of Rebellion, came back in the ſtill voice of Peace and Mercy: an happy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage how he would Govern. And theſe 23 or 24 years ſince his Return, might ſufficiently aſſure us of his meek Temper, <hi>by whom his very Enemies</hi> (as the worſt of them once truly ſaid) <hi>muſt acknowledge they fall gently:</hi> How have all his Subjects ſate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their own Vines, enjoyed peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whilſt all Chriſtendom beſides hath been harraſs'd with all the plagues of War? And now my Beloved, one would think, nothing but Praiſes to God for Mercies paſt, and Prayers for the preſervation of our gracious King, ſhould be heard in this our <hi>Sion;</hi> But inſtead of Grapes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nothing in ſome men but Thornes, inſtead of Figs, Thiſtles and Brambles, for Praiſes to God for Mercies paſt, vve have Murmurers, and Repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, inſtead of Prayers to God for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this our King; Blunderbuſſes are provided by Men of the old Leven to deſtroy his Perſon, with his Royal Brother: Plenty hath turned men into Wantonneſs, and our Troubles, like <hi>Jeſurun,</hi> vvhen fat, mutiny and raiſe Forces, not to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port but to demoliſh and ruin the Government: The Iſraelites grumbled, though fed with the food
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62462:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Angels, and our Malecontents are repining and talk of ſlavery, which cannot be dreaded from any but themſelves, and are not ſatisfied in a good Land flowing vvith all Plenty; vvhere there is no vvant, but of grateful Hearts to acknowledge it: Upon this a Conſpiracy is formed in our Iſrael, our vvicked men have their Cabals and Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words indeed not expreſſed in this 16 <hi>Chap.</hi> but ſufficiently implyed too. Our Conſpirators follow the ſame path, as their fore-Fathers in this <hi>Chap.</hi> but there is this difference between this Conſpiracy of theirs, and our wicked men, that of theirs was a Single, whilſt this of ours is a Complication of many Conſpiracies in one, you may call it Legion: and though there be a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Antipathy between the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent</hi> with other Sects, yet all of them, like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> though at never ſo great variance before, yet when Chriſt is to be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or when Chriſts Church is to be deſtroyed, and the nurſing Father thereof, Gods anointed, to be aſſaulted, and a Diſpute about the Crown to be raiſed, become Friends and are reconciled: <hi>Ferguſon</hi> ſupplies the place of <hi>Korah,</hi> and three Lords with three Commoners ſerve inſtead of <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> and <hi>On,</hi> the Conſpirators mentioned in <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. Nay, you may find other Conſpirators in our wicked men; who are repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62462:13"/>by <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Achitophel,</hi> the moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant can tell: The People too are to be allured by the ſame Arts as formerly: the Biſhops here, as <hi>Aaron</hi> in this <hi>Chap.</hi> are cried down, with, <hi>Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Congregation is Holy, even every one of them:</hi> The thirty fifth of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that ſtrong bulwark of our Engliſh Church againſt all the Batteries and Aſſaults of her Enemies, muſt be abrogated, and the Diſſenters humoured with an Act of Comprehenſion or Coalition; thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of more than Eighty-eight years old (ſo old that King <hi>James,</hi> at the Conference at <hi>Hamton-Court,</hi> with wonder asked them, when they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Men) I ſay theſe muſt ſtill be fed with Milk; their weak Stomachs cannot digeſt Ceremonies, though few, Innocent, and Primitive, when at the ſame time they are ſtrong enough to murder their King with his Royal Brother, and ſwallow a Maſſacre of thoſe that were truly loyal: And then how formidable and dangerous muſt this Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy be? if you believe one of the Traytors at his Execution, he will tell you that the Poyſon had ſpread it ſelf throughout the vvhole three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: Too too many of the lower Houſe of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Sanhedrim were infected; God grant for the future, they may be ſenſible of their Duty, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Heats and Bills of Excluſion, inſtead of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigning their fellow Subjects at their Bar; becauſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62462:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>they would not be ſo impudent, as to teach their King how to Rule, but ſubmitted the calling of Parliaments to his pleaſure, to whom it alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed; inſtead of rendering the King by their Votes more deſpicable than the meaneſt Subject; when men forſooth muſt <hi>be accounted betrayers of the liberty of the Subject, who ſhould truſt the King with any Money,</hi> I ſay, inſtead of theſe and the like proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, may that Houſe, like <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the defeat of <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s Conſpiracy, ſtrive with the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which of them may plead their intereſt beſt by their Service and Loyalty to the King: But of all Parts of the Kingdom, no place drank deeper of this poyſonous Conſpiracy than this City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> How have the Factious here for theſe laſt years ſtrugled with Authority? How did they endeavour to blaſt thoſe Perſons who adhered to the King, and were not ſo tame as to ſubmit the Laws, the Government, and their own throats too, to theſe wicked men, <hi>with the infamous Titles of Papiſts in Maſquerade, of lovers of Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and I know not what? how inſolent have they been by their tumultuary Petitions, by their riotous choice of Sheriffs, that <hi>Aſylum</hi> of theirs, to which theſe wicked Men, as of old at <hi>Rome,</hi> might fly, and if they were queſtioned for their Treaſons, <hi>an Ignoramus Jury might bring them off?</hi> But being baffled and diſappointed in theſe their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62462:14"/>ways, by the great Wiſdom with which God hath bleſſed our King, and by the indefatigable Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of faithful Subjects who durſt be as eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Loyal, as theſe were notoriouſly wicked, they are forced to alter their Meaſures.</p>
               <p>In theſe ſtreights and perplexities, methinks I hear <hi>Ferguſon,</hi> the Engliſh or Scotiſh <hi>Korah,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Conſpirators after this manner: My Lords, and Gentlemen, Let not your hearts fail you, that you have been ſo often diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; what we have already done, may ſufficiently declare, that we dare do more, and let not our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies flatter themſelves that they are ſecure; No, no, our City Charter is not ſo far loſt, but it may yet be recovered. 'Tis true indeed, we cannot any longer, under the pretence of Law, get the upper hand; but there is ſtill a way left to crown our Deſigns: a Blunderbuſs muſt effect what the pretence of Law did fail in; not to amuſe you any longer, the King with his Brother muſt be aſſaſſinated: Startle not, I ſay, the King himſelf muſt be taken off, and that <hi>for the ſaving the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtian Blood,</hi> otherwiſe you know he will puniſh, whom he will call the Murderers of his Brother. When they are taken off, nothing can oppoſe us; We have Forces ready, <hi>with an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred old Officers,</hi> who are fleſhed with the Blood of the old King, who eaſily vvill ſlay all our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarys,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62462:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>when the Loyaliſts, as they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſhall have none to Head them, or to whom they ſhall pay their obſtinate Allegiance any longer: And when the Blow is given, <hi>how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily may we throw</hi> (if you pleaſe to call it) <hi>the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the King, with the Duke, upon the Papiſts:</hi> This way (and no other) is ſo feaſible, that I cannot doubt but quickly to ſee you owned <hi>as the Deliverers of our Country.</hi> Upon this, you may imagine the Kings Death, with his Brothers, is concluded on; And another Royal Martyr, with his Brother, is to be added to the Sacred Calendar; the <hi>Rye</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire,</hi> is to be the Stage whereon this Tragedy muſt be acted; a place wherein they flattered themſelves they could not miſs of the Royal Prey; a place ſo convenient for their damnable intent, as if it were pointed out unto them by the Father of Darkneſs: Upon the thoughts of this place, our Conſpirators, with the Atheiſt in the Pſalmiſt, might flatter themſelves with the deſigned ſlaughter, as if God could not ſee them, and as if there were no knowledge in the Almighty, the not only Protector of Princes in general, but (be it ſpoken to Gods Glory and our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort) in particular, of our preſent King. Thus you have a deſcription of a Copy far tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Original; the Fanatick Conſpirators in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62462:15"/>
                  <hi>England</hi> far out-doing theſe wicked men whom my Text mentions: Now,</p>
               <p n="2">2. See whether theſe Wicked Men be not alſo conſumed in their Sins: Theſe Conſpirators, without doubt, longed for the day wherein they might ſacrifice the Lord's anointed: Their forces are ready in the City, ſo many perſons allotted to ſo many places, to follow the Murther of the King, and his Royal Brother, with an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Maſſacre: Nay, ſo ſure were they of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing their Deſigns, that they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to ſhift the fact from themſelves upon others; when alas, <hi>Good, good Men, they would no more have deſtroyed this King, than they really mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered his Father!</hi> Methinks I ſee theſe wicked Men, upon the thoughts of the murther of the King, and his Brother, with the following Maſſacre, hugging one another, and hear them ſaying, Now, now is the time that the <hi>Tory</hi>'s (ſo they were pleaſed to nick-name all thoſe that were truly Loyal) ſhall pay to the uttermoſt for all the diſappointments they have given us. <hi>The Lord Keeper ſhall expiate the Blood of</hi> Colledge <hi>upon the ſame Tree; the Judges, with Sir</hi> John Moore, <hi>ſhall be flead alive, and their skins being ſtuff'd, ſhall be hung up in</hi> Guild-hall. The <hi>Preſent Sheriffs</hi> ſhall wiſh they had never been ſo fool-hardy as to execute that office, and <hi>Pilkington</hi>'s Fine ſhall be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62462:15"/>made up with many of their Lives, as well as Eſtates. The Biſhops in vain ſhall wiſh that they had been for the Bill of Excluſion, the thorough-pac'd Clergy ſhall feel what it is to have preach'd up Paſſive Obedience ſo long, and the Lieutenancy ſhall rue their ſo often entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and all the Abhorrers of our Proceedings, ſhall to their ruine find what it is to oppoſe us.</p>
               <p>But the great God of Heaven, who had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo often preſerved our King, laughs now at the Policies of theſe Monſters, he blaſts their deſigns, and fruſtrates their expectations, and ſuffers no hands of violence to hurt his Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>A Fire at</hi> New-market, <hi>like the Angel that haſtened</hi> Lot <hi>out of</hi> Sodom, <hi>forceth the King with his Royal Brother, to come back to</hi> White-hall <hi>ſooner than he intended,</hi> and ſo were the Conſpirators diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. Thus God brings him ſafely back again, that ſo he might be now looked upon by his Subjects, not only as Gods Ordinance, but his Gift, (as the Ingenious as well as Pious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilers of this Service expreſs it) Upon this, one of the Conſpirators could not but ſee the finger of God, and that it was in vain to deſign any hurt to him, who had God for his Protector; thereupon he diſcovers the Plot, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers confeſs the ſame, every one as they were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62462:16"/>more or leſs engaged in it: Four of them have been Tryed, found Guilty, and received the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, as vvell as juſt vvages of Rebellion: Several of them are in priſon for the ſame Crime; one arraigns himſelf at the Bar of his ovvn Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and proves his ovvn Judge and Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner too; vvhileſt the greateſt Traytor of them dyes, I grant in his Bed, but I pray God (vvhat the laſt Lord Chancellour, vvhen Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, ſaid of ſome of the Murderers of the old King) it be not the vvorſe for him that he dyed in Peace, and that he did not in ſome manner in this World expiate his Treaſon vvith his Blood. The other Traytors vvander up and dovvn like <hi>Cain,</hi> bearing a mark in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, and fearing every one they ſee.</p>
               <p>Thus, Beloved, you have ſeen our vvicked Conſpirators conſumed in their ſins; and novv vvhat gratitude, vvhat thanks do vve ovve to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God for this ſignal Mercy vve novv com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate? If the deliverance of the King, vvith his Royal Brother: If the putting a ſtop to the Maſſacre of thoſe vvho adhered to their Prince in theſe perillous times: If the preſervation of our Religion from the Impoſture of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and I knovv not hovv many other Factions: If the ſecurity of our Liberty and Property un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Lavvful Prince: If theſe have any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62462:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>weight, as ſure they muſt with all honeſt and Loyal Men: Why then let us ſend up our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to Almighty God, that he will ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect his Anointed, and keep him under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of his Wings: Let no <hi>Aristodemuſes,</hi> no Murmurers or Repiners appear amongſt us: But if there be any amongſt us, who inſtead of giving Glory to God, for the diſcovery of this Fanatical and Helliſh Plot, do play the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> in this 16th Chapter, and ſeem to be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the puniſhment of Traytors, I wiſh to God they would ſeriouſly advert, and conſider the 49th verſe of this Chapter, where they will find that no leſs than 14700 were deſtroyed, becauſe they maliciouſly cryed out againſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> that they had killed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, and what people were they, <hi>why even the Bleſſed Conſpirators,</hi> Korah, <hi>and his Accomplices?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good God; that any ſhould be ſo bold, or fooliſh to call theſe, whom the Holy Ghoſt in my Text brands with the Character of Wicked Men, the People of the Lord: No, no, they never were, nor can be the People of the Lord, who reſiſt lawful Authority. What ſhall I ſay of thoſe who would aſſaſſinate Princes? Let us, O let us therefore aſſent to the advice of my Text, let us with the Elders here of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> follow our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62462:17"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh Moſes,</hi> and depart, as he commands us by his Laws, from the Tents, or Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of thoſe wicked men; let us not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with thoſe who are given to change, but abandon all thoſe Doctrines, whether vented by the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> that ſhall any ways withdraw or ſeduce us from our Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Let our thoughts of God's ſo often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving our King, render him the more dear unto us, and let us ſtrive to be as dutiful to him, as he hath been gracious to us in his Government. Let the Remembrance of Gods conſuming wicked Conſpirators in my Text, and his conſtant appearance in the reſcuing of his anointed ones, eſpecially our King, from the hands of Violence, not only deterr Wicked Men from their diſloyalty, but ſpur on, and encourage Obedient Subjects in the proſecution of their Duties to their Sovereign.</p>
               <p>If any hereafter offer to ſeduce any of you from your obedience to your Ruler, tell ſuch an one, that God Almighty ſtill protects Princes, eſpecially this preſent King: Tell him, that Traytors and Conſpirators are ſtill conſumed in their ſins in this World; and if that will not throw off the Tempter, tell him, That you dare not be eternally damned.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62462:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>For Concluſion of all, let me ſpeak a word or two by way of Exhortation, to thoſe that have been, or now being convinced of their errours, do deſire to ſhew themſelves Loyal to the King: Wouldſt thou (O Subject) have the King preſerved, and long, and happily reign over his people, why then let me (as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid in the like caſe to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>) adviſe you to be Religious towards God, <hi>Abhor that which is evil, cleave to that which is good, do Juſtice, love Mercy, and walk humbly with God. If ye do well,</hi> ſaid <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, ye and your King ſhall live.</hi> Never, O ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flatter thy ſelf that thou canſt truly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King, unleſs thou feareſt God; for as there is no ſuch thing as a Rebellious people of the Lord, ſo neither can there be a wicked Loyaliſt. Do not, O do not pretend to be Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to your Prince, if you be diſobedient to God: Every vain Oath that you ſwear, may prove a Dagger; every Whoredome, or Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, every Oppreſſion of the Poor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may prove a Blunderbuſs to your King; and not only ſo, but deſtructive to your Bodies and Souls eternally.</p>
               <p>Therefore, for your King's ſake, nay, for your own Bodies and Souls ſake eternally; if you have followed ſin hitherto, break from it now: Let us repent us of our evil ways, and put
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62462:18"/>on firm Reſolutions, never to commit the ſame Crimes again: This if we do, both our King and we ſhall live: Which God grant, through the Merit and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>There are ſome few faults eſcap'd, which the Reader is deſir'd to amend thus: <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>read</hi> Theocratical. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>read</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. <hi>p.</hi> 8. l. 24. <hi>read</hi> Parity. <hi>p.</hi> 20. l. 25. <hi>read</hi> Troublers.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62462:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62462:19"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and ſold by <hi>James Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> at the <hi>King's Arms</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>MAſſinello;</hi> or a Satyr againſt the Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Riot, 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eromena:</hi> or the Noble Stranger. A curious Novel. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Tractatus adverſus Reprobationis abſolutae decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Nova Methodo &amp; ſuccentiſimo Compendio adorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; &amp; in duos Libros digeſtus. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. An <hi>Idea</hi> of Happineſs, in a Letter to a Friend, enquiring wherein the greateſt Happineſs attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by man in this Life does conſiſt. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A Murnival of Knaves, or Whiggiſm plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſplay'd, and (if not grown ſhameleſs) Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſqu'd out of Countenance. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Haec &amp; Hic;</hi> or the Feminine <hi>Gender</hi> more worthy than the Maſculine; being a Vindication of that ingenious and innocent Sex from the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sarcaſms, bitter Satyrs, and opprobrious Calumnies, wherewith they are daily (tho un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſervedly) aſpers'd by the Virulent Tongues and Pens of malevolent men. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Patria Parricida:</hi> or the Hiſtory of the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Conſpiracy of <hi>Catiline</hi> againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
